If you're investing through one of the
big Canadian banks, you will want to
watch this video. Investigative
journalism, research from Canadian
regulators, and academic research all
suggest that banks are more focused on
selling products that are good for the
bank than on giving advice in the best
interest of their customers. The result
is that Canadians taking advice from
their banks, as many Canadians do, are
often being sold suboptimal, high fee
products by salespeople with limited
expertise in portfolio management and
financial planning. This is a problem
worth addressing. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital, and
I'm going to tell you how the sales
culture at Canadian banks may be
affecting the advice bank financial
adviserss provide to Canadians.
[Music]
I do want to be clear that we are
talking about retail bank branches.
Think about walking into a bank branch
and asking to meet with a financial
adviser in the branch. I also want to
mention that the information in this
video does not mean that there are not
some good financial adviserss working at
bank branches. I know they do exist
because my firm PWL Capital has hired
some of them. The incentive structure
and sales culture within banks rather
than the advisers themselves seem to be
a big part of the problem that I'm going
to highlight in this video. In a March
2024 investigation, CBC News found that
customers at Canada's big five banks,
TD, RBC, Scotia Bank, Beimo, and CIBC
were being pressured to buy financial
products they did not need. And the bank
employees were being told to push those
products and services to meet sales
targets or risk losing their jobs. The
result is that bank employees were found
to be giving questionable advice like
telling people to invest in the bank's
mutual funds or GIC's instead of paying
off highinterest debt, misrepresenting
the importance of mutual fund fees to
expect investment outcomes, and
upselling customers on more expensive
financial products. Bank employees
really don't seem to be malicious based
on the CBC investigation. Some of them
who are interviewed by CBC News are
stressed out by the pressure to sell at
all costs. Based on some of the comments
by bank financial adviserss on mutual
fund fees and expected returns, I
suspect that beyond conflicts of
interest, a lack of education
contributes to the quality of advice.
Some of the bank financial adviserss
captured by CBC's investigation did not
seem to know how mutual fund fees work
or had unrealistic return expectations
for mutual funds. One adviser even said
that mutual fund fees are nothing to
worry about, which is of course not
true. This CBC investigative reporting
is based on a relatively small sample
and one could argue that it may not be
representative of typical bank financial
advice. In November 2024, in response to
CBC's reporting, the Ontario Securities
Commission and the Canadian Investment
Regulatory Organization teamed up to
coordinate a more systematic review of
the sales practices at bank affiliated
mutual fund dealers. They conducted a
voluntary anonymous survey sent to all
mutual fund dealing representatives
working in one of the bank branches at
five of Canada's bank affiliated mutual
fund dealers in Ontario. The survey
asked bank mutual fund representatives
about the sales environment, sales
pressure, and product availability in
their bank branches and also asked
questions designed to assess the
knowledge of the representatives. It was
completed by 2,863
respondents, offering a much broader
cross-section than CBC's reporting. The
results did not show significant
differences across banks or regions,
leading the study's authors to suggest
that the results and implications of the
analysis are applicable across Ontario
and across all five of the big bank
affiliated mutual fund dealers. You can
basically assume that the research
applies to most bank financial
adviserss. An interesting aspect of the
report is that it details the average
bank mutual fund representative. Based
on the survey sample, on average, they
hold one professional designation or
credential, commonly the Canadian
Securities Course or an equivalent,
which is the bare minimum to sell mutual
funds in Canada. They have six years of
work experience as a mutual fund
representative. 10% of their total
compensation is variable, including
things like bonuses and profit sharing.
And they typically offer other financial
products, including mortgages, lines of
credit, credit cards, bank accounts, and
GIC's in addition to mutual funds. Only
9% of representatives hold other
credentials, most often the CFP, and
those representatives are more likely to
offer planning based services. The main
results of the survey are wild. 32% of
representatives agree that the way
representatives are compensated places
more value on sales volume than on the
quality of advice given to clients.
About half of representatives, 47%,
strongly disagree that the way they are
compensated could create an incentive to
prioritize sales goals over client
interests. Well, 34% agree. One in three
representatives agree that the way they
are compensated could create incentives
for representatives to prioritize sales
and revenue targets over client
interests. And 35% of representatives
agree that the way they are compensated
may increase the risk that
recommendations made to clients are not
suitable for those clients. I think most
people would expect this type of
incentive system when buying a car, but
not for financial advice. 68% of
representatives say they experience
sales pressure at least sometimes and
35% experience it often or always. 44%
agree that there is a fear of job loss
due to not being able to meet sales,
revenue, client or asset targets. 23%
agree that there is high pressure to
sell potentially unneeded products or
services to clients. And 25% indicate
that clients have been recommended
products or services that are not in
their interests at least sometimes. If
you're a consumer of bank financial
advice, that is a scary statistic. 25%
of bank mutual fund representatives
surveyed said that clients have been
sold products that are not in the
client's best interest, at least
sometimes. The study does also find an
unsurprising relationship between sales
pressure and advice not in the client's
best interest. Representatives who
reported experiencing higher levels of
sales pressure were more likely to agree
that clients have been recommended
products or services that are not in
their interests. A majority, 55% of
respondents reported having concerns
related to sales pressure at least
sometimes, while 25% reported having
these concerns often or always. A large
portion of these concerned
representatives are reluctant to raise
their concerns at their workplace due to
the fear of reprisal. And of those that
have raised concerns, 43% of them
indicated that their concerns were
addressed rarely or never. All things
considered, the results show that most
of the mutual fund representatives
working for one of the big five banks
have at minimum some concerns related to
sales pressure in their roles. Many of
them are reluctant to raise these
concerns in the workplace. And among
those who have voiced their concerns,
nearly half of them feel that their firm
has not appropriately address their
concerns. Sales pressure is definitely
one thing that bank customers should be
deeply concerned about. But even in the
absence of sales pressure, many bank
mutual fund representatives are simply
limited in the investment products they
can offer. Bank advisers are often
limited to using bank funds. This makes
sense for the bank, but not necessarily
for their clients. 78% of
representatives surveyed say that their
existing range of product meets the
needs of their clients, but almost half
of them do agree that clients would
benefit if they could be offered a
broader range of mutual funds, including
mutual funds from providers other than
the bank. This just makes sense. A
bank's mutual funds, which are often
going to be high fee actively managed
funds, might be useful in some cases
maybe, but it's hard to argue that
limiting the available products to the
bank's funds is a good thing for
clients. This Canadian regulatory study
is supported by past academic research.
A 2018 paper in the Review of Financial
Studies uses data from a large retail
bank to analyze how banks and their
financial advisers generate profits from
customers. The authors find that
transactions initiated by bank advisers
earn the bank higher profits than
independently executed trades placed by
the same client. Unsurprisingly, the
bank's own mutual funds and structured
products are the most profitable
products for the bank. Bank profits
increase with trade size and bank
advisers recommend transactions that are
profitable for the bank. If these
profitable transactions were also making
clients better off, it would be easy to
argue that there is no issue here. But
the research finds that bank advised
clients have worse performance than
unadvised clients, suggesting again that
advisers put the bank's interests before
the clients. I want to mention again
that these issues are more with the
incentive structure and the sales
culture at the banks than with the
advisers themselves. I don't think bank
financial advisers are malicious even if
they are affected by conflicts of
interest. Their knowledge levels may
also be affecting their ability to
identify the conflicts and other issues
with their advice. About 80% of
representatives in the regulatory study
believe that their peers are
sufficiently knowledgeable on a variety
of financial topics, but onethird of
representatives reported that clients
have been provided with incorrect
information about products or services
being recommended to them at least
sometimes. And 23% of representatives
were unable to correctly identify the
definition of a management expense ratio
or me, one of the most important
attributes of a mutual fund. This also
lines up with academic research. The
2021 paper, the misguided beliefs of
financial adviserss, published in the
journal of finance, finds in a Canadian
sample of financial adviserss and their
clients, that advisers typically make
the same mistakes personally as they do
in their client accounts. They trade too
much. They chase past returns. They
prefer expensive, actively managed
mutual funds and they underdiversify
their portfolios. The advisers's
personal accounts underperform just as
poorly as their clients. The study also
shows that advisers continue to make
these mistakes after they leave the
financial services industry, suggesting
that they weren't just putting on a show
to convince clients to buy higher fee
products. They really believed in the
bad advice that they were selling. This
again suggests that conflicts of
interest are only part of the problem
and highlights the importance of raising
the educational bar for financial
adviserss. Solving where that bar should
be across the industry from a regulatory
perspective is a big job. I do think
some things are moving in the right
direction here in Canada, but investors
seeking advice can still look for
advisers with more than the bare minimum
regulatory credentials. Credible
credentials with rigorous credentiing
programs, ethical standards, and
enforcement for professional and ethical
conduct like the CFA and CFP are good
places to start. It is also worth noting
that how an adviser is registered does
matter. A discretionary portfolio
manager in Canada is generally held to a
higher legal standard with a deemed
common law fiduciary duty to their
clients than a non-discretionary mutual
fund representative. My hunch is that
many consumers assume that financial
advisers are required to act in their
best interest, but that is not always
the case. The good news for consumers is
that there are non-bank firms that
employ portfolio managers, use lowcost
investment products, and limit their
conflicts of interest. Acknowledging my
own biases here, as the chief investment
officer at PWL Capital, I think that PWL
is a great example. PWL's clients work
with portfolio managers whose
compensation is not tied to product
sales. We require our adviserss to have
advanced credentials like the CFA and
CFP, and we promote and pay for ongoing
education for our adviserss. It's part
of our culture. PWL even takes all this
a step further by getting independently
certified as placing our clients
interests first by the center for
fiduciary excellence. I've been part of
that annual audit and it is no joke. I'm
not saying that PWL is good because I
work for PWL. I work for PWL because I
think that the way this firm operates is
exactly how financial advice should be
provided to Canadians. I started out in
financial services with a
commission-based job selling insurance
and mutual funds. I had to sell high fee
actively managed products or insurance
if I wanted to eat. I feel for the bank
advisers in a similar position, but that
doesn't make raising awareness about the
problems with bank financial advice any
less important. What's important for
consumers to understand is that CBC News
investigative journalism and a recent
survey conducted by the OC and CRO
suggests that financial advisers at
branches of Canada's big five banks are
under heavy pressure to sell financial
products that are often not in the best
interest of their clients. One in four
representatives in a regulatory study
report that clients have been
recommended product or services that are
not in their interests. The study
suggests that this may be tied to the
sales environment within the five bank
affiliated dealers, including
compensation incentives and performance
metrics used. A high degree of pressure
to meet sales targets and the frequent
use of scorecards to track, compare, and
emphasize those sales targets. That kind
of sales culture and incentive structure
might be appropriate at a car
dealership, but at least in my opinion,
financial advice deserves a much higher
bar. Consumers should be looking for
adviserss with credentials like the CFA
or CFP who are employed by firms that
put their clients interests first,
encourage education for their adviserss,
and incentivize highquality advice over
product sales. Thanks for watching. I'm
Ben Felix, chief investment officer at
PWL Capital. If you found this
information useful, please share it with
someone who is still taking advice from
the bank.